ANNOUNCER : The following commentary is by Sir Christopher Frayling ,
film historian , expert on horror literature and film ,
and rector of the Royal College of Art in London .
FRAYLING : We begin with a prologue
with actor Edward Van Sloan
coming in front of the curtain and doing a partly teasing ,
partly titillating , partly warning to the audience
that what they 're about to see is a horror movie .
This was in fact added after the previews of Frankenstein
because the studio weren 't quite sure how to handle it .
The prologue was partly written by the young John Huston and others ,
and we don 't actually know who shot it .
It probably wasn 't James Whale .
Edward Van Sloan , veteran actor ,
50 years old , had appeared in at least 150 plays on Broadway ,
and had most recently appeared as Van Helsing in Universal 's Dracula .
The sort of authority figure .
Later , after appearing as Waldman in Frankenstein ,
he would appear as Muller in The Mummy .
So , he became the sort of authority figure in a whole cycle of Universal films .
But actually , the character he plays in Frankenstein is rather different
to the one he played in Dracula .
We begin the credits with a face with rays coming out of the eyes ,
just like the way in which Bela Lugosi had been filmed in Dracula ,
and just as the prologue begins where the end of Dracula finished off ,
with Edward Van Sloan saying , " There are such things , "
so the credits pick up on the visuals of Dracula .
And then we get these eyes in a circular motion .
Again , partly a reference to Bela Lugosi ,
reminding us of the previous Universal product .
But also a reference to a famous scene in Fritz Lang 's Metropolis , 1926 ,
the nightclub scene where the false Maria is doing an erotic dance ,
and the eyes circulate in this way .
So , already we 've got a reference to German expressionist films .
The credits show the rather convoluted history of this production .
It isn 't so much based on the novel by Mary Shelley ,
or Mrs. Percy B. Shelley , as they call her on the credits .
It 's more based on a series of plays , adaptations of Frankenstein ,
which had been happening since 1823 .
Most recently , one by Peggy Webling ,
adapted by the American journalist John L. Balderston .
The first scene , the graveyard scene ,
originally had shots of mourners on the horizon carrying a coffin
and bells and flags and banners and so on .
This was cut out and later reused
in the opening sequence of The Bride of Frankenstein .
Instead , we begin with a diagonal shot of a rope and a coffin ,
and we panned across the mourners . We have a cross at a crazy angle .
In fact , on the shooting script , it says , " Crosses are tottering at crazy angles ,
" and we are somewhere in central Europe . " There 's a figure of death in a monk 's cowl .
And just like the credits , we begin with eyes and hands coming down behind it .
As Fritz , played by Dwight Frye ,
who played the Renfield figure , the man who eats insects in Dracula ,
pops up with his pop-eyes .
He 's the man who had a stage whisper that could be heard three miles away .
And behind him , Colin Clive as Frankenstein .
The priest takes away the bell inside its sacramental cover ,
and , were it a Roman Catholic funeral somewhere in central Europe ...
We don 't know what period we are .
As the shooting script said , there 's an angry sky , it 's parched , there 's leafless trees .
And everything 's on the diagonal . Nothing 's vertical .
This is a tottering world that 's about to fall over .
And we now concentrate on the gravedigger .
The microphone was actually placed inside the coffin in order to get the echo effect
as the earth hits the casket , which rather shocked audiences in 1931 .
Remember that horror films hadn 't really caught on yet as a genre of entertainment ,
so it came as quite a surprise .
This is much more physical horror , much more realistic horror
than had been represented in Dracula .
This moment where the gravedigger lights his pipe
isn 't , in fact , in the shooting script .
It was added at the last minute by James Whale ,
and is the first of many references in this film to fire .
The lighting of the match , the flaming torches ,
the mill that burns down at the end ,
the fire from the heavens that gives the spark of life to the creature .
And , in fact , the original novel was called Frankenstein : or , the Modern Prometheus ,
and the whole myth of Prometheus is Prometheus brought down fire from the gods
and tried to bring it onto Earth and was punished for it ,
just like Frankenstein being punished for challenging the gods
in this piece of spare-part surgery that he engages in .
[ CHURCH BELL TOLLS ]
The bell in the background is also interesting .
It tolls mournfully for the funeral .
Later on , the Angelus will sing , there will be wedding bells ,
and the bell will toll mournfully at the end , as the mill goes up .
So , the sound design of the film was actually remarkably sophisticated for 1931 .
And we 're in for a more visual experience than Dracula was .
Although we 're in the studio at Universal ,
it owes a lot to German expressionist films of the ' 20s .
In fact , James Whale viewed The Cabinet of Dr. Caligari
when preparing Frankenstein , as reported in Variety .
The shooting script makes explicit reference to Metropolis in the laboratory scene .
And there 's no doubt that the creature owes a great deal to The Golem ,
the 1920 German film .
[ CLATTERING ]
The coffin being brought out of the grave isn 't in fact mentioned in the shooting script ,
and again , was added at the last minute .
Now , we 're not sure what period we 're in .
Throughout the film , there 's a strange elision of periods .
Yes , the women 's costumes are 1930 , 1931 .
Yes , the equipment looks very modern . But look , here 's a public hanging .
A body swinging on a gibbet up in the hills .
So , a sort of medieval or pre-18th century reference .
And throughout , you get this funny , dreamlike mixing it with historical periods .
The angry mob is medieval , the laboratory , the watchtower is Gothic ,
sort of 18th , 19th century .
The swinging corpse . And yet , a lot of modern things as well .
And although this is a film that deals with modern science ,
where are the radios ? Where are the cars ? Where are the telephones ?
Where are all the latest developments of science ? They 're not there at all .
We 're in a kind of never-never land that 's partly medieval , partly fairytale ,
and partly modern .
As James Whale said , " It 's all part of the ritual . "
This is an attempt to tell a fairy tale that 's timeless .
And we don 't know where we are either .
It says in the shooting script somewhere in central Europe .
In Peggy Webling 's play , we 're in Switzerland ,
Goldstadt in Switzerland .
In the novel , we 're in France and Switzerland and Germany ,
but it isn 't clear . It 's a kind of never-never land again ,
which is somewhere in central Europe .
But here to remind us we 're in Goldstadt , " Goldstadt Medical College . "
And a lecture theater .
Originally , in the shooting script , the cut was , in fact , to a domestic scene
involving Elizabeth , Frankenstein 's fiancée , and their friend , Victor .
But the order of the scenes was changed to bring in the university .
And here 's Dr. Waldman in action .
And the students not paying any attention . All this laughter and low comedy
was added after the shooting script .
And James Whale added lots of comedic moments to this film
in the lightweight scenes that punctuate the more dramatic Gothic scenes
throughout the film .
He heightened the comedy and he heightened the horror .
And we 're first introduced to these two brains .
The normal brain and the dysfunctio cerebri ,
the abnormal brain ,
which is nothing to do with the novel , nothing to do with the plays .
It was added on the original outline by Robert Florey ,
the French-American director who was originally slotted for Frankenstein .
And he had this idea that you 'd have a good brain and a bad brain ,
and the bad brain would be sewn into the hapless creature 's cranium .
This , of course , altered the entire point of the story
by making it a kind of eugenic thing .
You know , some brains are bad , some people are criminals by birth
for eugenic reasons .
Whereas in the story , it 's all about social responsibility .
The creature becomes ugly because he 's treated as ugly .
And if society rejects people and treats them as seriously disabled ,
then they 're liable to have a rather violent reaction ,
is the theme of the novel .
But in this , it 's all a matter of good brain and bad brain .
It cuts out about half a volume of story in just one tiny sequence .
And here we have Fritz , the vertically challenged laboratory assistant ,
rather like the puffer figure in alchemy , who stands doing the actual craftwork
white the scientist stands in the foreground .
Fritz , a character who goes right back to the original dramatization of Frankenstein
in 1823 , providing someone for Frankenstein to talk to during the laboratory scenes .
He 's taking the brain .
The bouncing skeleton in the background isn 't mentioned in the shooting script ,
another comedy moment , a sort of vaudeville moment , as Fritz ...
Actually , there 's a continuity error there .
It 's bouncing in one of the shots and not in the others .
But Fritz bumps into the skeleton .
So , this rather tense scene of pinching the wrong brain
is also punctuated by comedy , a very James Whale shift of mood .
James Whale loved extreme shifts of mood ,
from comedy to tragedy , from gruesomeness to laughter .
Comedies of manners , of eccentricity .
And so , in the next scene , we have a domestic scene ,
a lightweight scene to follow the nastiness of the laboratory .
And it begins with a series of close-ups
that aren 't again mentioned in the shooting script .
But Whale thought this was the most economic way of presenting
the domestic complexities of the relationships between these characters .
Close-up of the photo of Frankenstein , close-up of the maid ,
close-up of Elizabeth , played by Mae Clarke , close-up of Victor , played by John Boles .
And there 's something between these people .
Frankenstein is engaged to be married to Elizabeth ,
but Victor is a close friend of Elizabeth .
In fact , in the John Balderston adaptation ,
he 's the ex-fiancé of Elizabeth who has been jilted for Frankenstein .
All of that 's done in very quick close-ups at the beginning of the scene
prior to a long dialogue scene .
Mae Clarke had appeared in James Whale 's previous film , Waterloo Bridge ,
as the prostitute , Myra .
And she was having a hell of a year in 1931 , because 1931 was also the year
when she had a grapefruit pushed in her face by James Cagney
in Public Enemy .
She was , in fact , the original of the character Lorelei Lee , Mae Clarke was ,
in Gentlemen Prefer Blondes by Anita Loos ,
because in the 1920s , the mid - '20s , she was a song-and-dance girl
in vaudeville and nightclubs . And the Lorelei Lee character was based upon her .
James Whale cast her in this .
She was slightly apprehensive that she was playing an English character ,
or someone who should speak Shakespearean English , Elizabeth ,
But Whale said , " Don 't worry about that . "
But he cast her because she had an intensity and a kind of shrillness in her performance .
And , as he said , she believed so wholeheartedly in this project ,
she wasn 't going to send it up , that he cast her in preference to Bette Davis ,
who was the actress who was first mentioned with reference to this part .
John Boles was a singer as well as an actor ,
a baritone who appeared in numerous musicals at this time .
And he represents stolid support as Victor .
In Peggy Webling 's play , the names of the characters were juggled around
from the original Mary Shelley novel in all sorts of strange ways .
Victor Frankenstein becomes Henry Frankenstein .
Victor is given to the friend ,
Moritz , which was the surname of the servant in the novel Frankenstein ,
is given as the surname to Victor .
And Henry , which was the name of Henry Clerval ,
Frankenstein 's closest friend , who is murdered by the creature ,
the name is given to Frankenstein .
So Frankenstein becomes Henry , the friend becomes Victor ,
Elizabeth was always Elizabeth ,
except that she 's called Amelia in the John Balderston version ,
if you follow me .
But I don 't know why the names were changed .
Victor is such a good name for the overreaching scientist ,
but in this film , he becomes Henry Frankenstein .
I 'll be ready in a minute .
Herr Frankenstein is a most ...
FRAYLING : And James Whale wanted to build up the Mae Clarke character ,
so he added her to this scene where they visit Dr. Waldman
in his office / laboratory .
Strange mixture again of medieval-modern . Look at the skulls on the shelf behind him ,
and the test tubes in the foreground .
It 's like a medieval image of an alchemist in the background , and in the foreground ,
some images of modern science .
But Elizabeth is there expressing her worries about her fiancé .
And Victor is giving his usual solid support .
Herr Frankenstein is greatly changed .
FRAYLING : Waldman comes over not as a sympathetic Van Helsing character ,
but right from the beginning , as a rather dogmatic elder statesman
who rushes to judgment .
And throughout this film , he tends to say ,
" Kill the monster ! " and " It 's going to be a danger to society . "
" Destroy ! Destroy ! "
And he has a very extreme view . He 's not the voice of reason .
He doesn 't believe that truth lies in the middle .
He tends to adopt rather extreme positions .
And Waldman introduces , in this sequence , the first sustained reference
to the mythological world that this film belongs to ,
linking it to older scenarios of forbidden knowledge .
Going back to the Garden of Eden ,
or the classical myths of Prometheus , Daedalus and Icarus .
If you overreach , you 're going to get burned .
If you deal with knowledge that you shouldn 't ,
you 're going to get into trouble .
In fact , the original novel Frankenstein wasn 't too concerned with this theme ,
this Faustian theme , this theme of overreaching .
It had lots of other themes .
The personal responsibility of the artist and scientist ,
The social responsibility of the scientist .
The acquisition of language through the creature
and educational theories .
Social radicalism and radical social theory coming from her father , William Godwin .
It had all these themes , and indeed , themes about contemporary science .
But the Faustian theme was just one of many .
Through Waldman , it becomes foregrounded as the main point of the story .
And it really sets the tone for mad scientist films from then on .
They 're Faustian films . Nature , good . Science can be bad .
And you mustn 't overreach . There are limits to the kind of knowledge that 's permissible ,
and you 're somehow challenging God if you go further .
In fact , God is scarcely mentioned in Mary Shelley 's novel .
It 's a kind of Romantic , slightly godless universe of overreachers .
The overreaching takes place in this world , not the next .
But there are many references to God ,
including a famous one in this sequence , during the film .
- Fritz ! - Hello .
[ RATTLING ]
Have you finished making those connections ?
Yes , they 're done .
Well , come down then and help with these ...
FRAYLING : Now , the laboratory has a fascinating history .
In the original novel , Mary Shelley simply wrote ,
" I gathered the instruments of life around me . "
That 's all she said about the equipment in the laboratory .
She wasn 't interested in the literalness of how the operation happened .
It was more a mythic fairytale moment .
Subsequently , she talked about the workings of some great engine in 1831 ,
when she reintroduced the novel in its cut-down version .
In the play of 1823 , there 's lots of sparks and flames , but they happen offstage ,
and Fritz tells the audience what 's going on , and suddenly the creature staggers in
through the doors of the laboratory .
In film , in 1910 , the Edison version of Frankenstein
made the laboratory into an alchemist laboratory .
You had a bubbling cauldron , and out of the cauldron comes the creature .
And indeed , in the John Balderston adaptation ,
from which the film was taken , it 's a mixture of sparks and electricity ,
and also the elixir of life , a liquid that 's poured into the creature 's mouth .
But for this film , it 's all modern science .
And James Whale reckoned the entire credibility of the film
depended on this sequence .
If the audience could believe that the creature
was actually having the spark of life , the vitalism of life , put into him ,
then the story would hold together .
If they didn 't believe that , they would simply laugh and say ,
" This is too farfetched , I can 't even watch this film . "
So , the creation sequence was absolutely crucial .
Where did he get it from ?
Well , partly , he got it from Metropolis in 1926 ,
where there 's a long laboratory sequence where the scientist ,
Dr. Rotwang , played by Rudolf Klein-Rogge ,
dressed in a medieval jerkin in a Gothic house in the middle of a modern city
creates an artificial Maria , an artificial robot ,
by transferring essence of real Maria into robot Maria .
And there 's lots of bubbling glassware .
Lots of electric sparks and arcs which are visible .
No sound effects , of course , it was a silent film .
And in fact , the person responsible for the special effects in Metropolis said ,
" The great challenge is how do you visualize electricity ? "
Electricity is invisible . How do you visualize it ?
You 've got to have sparks , you 've got to have arcs .
You 've got to make the audience see electricity .
So , they contacted the electrical engineer and inventor Kenneth Strickfaden ,
who put together the equipment for this laboratory .
It 's all sorts of things . He said any junk that he happened to have around
was put into the styling of it .
And he used all sorts of phrase .
There 's a baritone generator , whatever that is .
There 's a vacuum electrolysis and there 's a nucleus analyzer .
None of these words really mean anything , it 's a kind of mumbo jumbo .
And actually , if you look at the shooting script ,
it has a very impressionistic view of what should be in the laboratory .
A glittering , mysterious apparatus with generators , transformers ,
wave-chargers , diffusers , a large rotary spark gap , et cetera .
Very impressive-looking .
It 's more impressionistic than scientific ,
designed to create a feeling of modern scientific magic .
Something suggestive of the laboratory in Metropolis .
[ POUNDING ON DOOR ]
Not much .
I 'll show them , messing about at this time of night .
Got too much to do .
Wait a minute ! All right ! All right !
FRAYLING : Fritz goes down the stairs ,
and a lot of business is added by James Whale after the shooting script .
A lot of comedy after the intensity of the laboratory scene .
This huge staircase , which owes a lot in fact to The Golem of 1920 ,
and Fritz , stumbling around in the night .
And here we have a very typical James Whale bit of business . As he goes up the steps ,
he pulls up his sock , and then continues up the steps .
Again , that might have been improvised ,
it was certainly added at the last minute in August , 1931 .
Henry !
ELIZABETH : Open the door !
FRAYLING : We 're in the watchtower on the hill .
In the original Robert Florey version ,
it was the mill , where the film finishes , that the laboratory was located in .
In Mary Shelley 's novel , it 's the upstairs room of Frankenstein 's house .
But here it 's a watchtower on a hill .
Remember , the word Frankenstein means " the rock " or " stone of the Franks . "
They are the people of the mountains ,
the people who live amongst the rocks and stones .
And of course , it has to be a high place , the highest you can find ,
in order to harness the vitalism of the heavens .
The design of the sets by art director Charles D. Hall ,
with Herman Rosse doing the drawings ,
and James Whale , who himself was a trained scene designer and had been to art school ,
supervising it , is one of the most memorable aspects of this film .
From German expressionism in the ' 20s , where everything is on the diagonal ,
where you have painted sets , where the madness of the sets
is an outward and a visible sign of the madness of the characters .
It moves on , in this film , into a kind of camp version of expressionism .
A kind of camp Gothic with everything a bit larger than life .
Huge vertical spaces , diagonal beams , lots of shadows .
And this became one of the trademarks of Charles D. Hall , or Danny Hall .
He was an architect from Norwich , England ,
who had gone over to Canada with his brother .
His brother became construction manager at Universal Studios ,
and Danny Hall became the overall art director or design manager of the studio .
And apparently , they used to have arguments on the set because the brother would say ,
" I can 't make it like that , I 'm going to make it like this , "
and alter the designs as he made them . But it was all in good part .
Hall had cut his teeth in the ' 20s on The Phantom of the Opera ,
where he contributed to the opera house , the famous opera house set ,
and The Hunchback of Notre Dame ,
where he contributed to the great set of Notre Dame Cathedral ,
but I think most of his ideas came from the German director Paul Leni ,
who came over to Universal in 1927 and directed The Cat and the Canary ,
which Charles Danny Hall designed .
So , the visualization is such a strong aspect of this
and set a kind of brand image for Universal Studios
at a time when the studios were finding a visual corporate image ,
the big white set of MGM , the Bauhaus of Paramount .
Well , Danny Hall 's Gothic
became the corporate image of Universal , and remained so really until the late ' 30s ,
when the Laemmles sold the studio .
You said I was crazy .
- Tomorrow we 'll see about that . - [ SHOUTS ] Don 't touch that !
[ THUNDER RUMBLING ]
I 'm sorry , Doctor ...
FRAYLING : James Whale wrote , " I consider the creation of The Monster
" to be the high spot of the film "
" because if the audience didn 't believe the thing had really been made , "
" they wouldn 't be bothered with what it was supposed to do afterwards . "
" Frankenstein merely has to believe what he sees , "
" which is all we ask the audience to do . "
When Whale wrote to Colin Clive asking if he 'd take the part ,
they 'd worked together on the play and film Journey 's End ,
where Clive played this over-the-top , tense , shrill Captain Stanhope ,
who is shell-shocked in his dugout in the First World War
and has become an alcoholic .
Whale wrote to him , " Frankenstein is a grand part
" and I think it will fit you as well as Stanhope .
" I see Frankenstein as an intensely sane person , but at times rather fanatical
" and in one or two scenes , a little hysterical .
" In the first scene in the lab , he becomes very conscious of the theatrical drama ,
" and goes a little insane about it .
" There are none of Dracula 's maniacal cackles .
" I want it all to be very modern , materialistic treatment of this medieval story ,
" something of Dr. Caligari , something of Edgar Allan Poe
" and , of course , a good deal of us . "
" Us " being the relationship they 'd developed when making Journey 's End
on the London stage , the New York stage and in the film ,
which had been made a couple of years before ,
and which got James Whale his contract with Universal .
But it 's the theatricality of this that is so surprising , in a way .
Frankenstein is setting up the scene , both for the audience
and for Waldman , Victor and Elizabeth .
He sets up the chairs so that Elizabeth , Waldman and Victor can watch ,
and Frankenstein talks about , " Watch the show , "
in fact , in the shooting script , he says ,
" The overture begins , " and you get this overture of thunder .
No music , there 's no music in this film at all , which is very surprising .
There 's a piece of specially written music behind the credits ,
a misterioso piece , and a piece of music at the end credits ,
which was an off-the-shelf piece from silent cinema , an appassionato ,
but it 's thunder , it 's natural sounds during the actual film .
One man crazy , and there 's the audience watching him .
And so , the audience sitting in the laboratory becomes a surrogate
for the audience in the cinema .
- Watch the show . - [ THUNDER RUMBLING ]
Get the batteries .
FRAYLING : This , I suppose , is the most famous sequence
in the entire film ,
where the designs of Danny Hall and Herman Rosse ,
the bits of engineering bric-a-brac from Kenneth Strickfaden ,
the tense , hysterical performance of Colin Clive ,
a long way away from the young research student ,
the cool , young research student in Mary Shelley 's original novel .
This is a much more mature figure , kind of manic old Etonian
who chain-smokes and goes completely over-the-top like Stanhope .
Instead of the First World War , it 's science that 's turned his head ,
although he is completely sane .
And Fritz , scurrying around as the laboratory assistant , the puffer ,
all these things come together .
In the script , it says that the table is lifted 12 to 15 feet above floor level ,
but just look at this , right up into the roof of the watchtower .
A hugely vertical set . Very , very large .
James Whale and Danny Hall were really thinking on a grand scale
of these sets .
[ THUNDER RUMBLING ]
" It says in the script , " Sparks crackle , rotary sparks make snapping circles of fire .
" Great electrical display on glass rings around the table crackle with intense heat . "
And , in the script , the idea is that the corpse lying on the surgical table
is all black when it goes up in the air ,
and when it comes down , it 's gone white .
A symbol of the life being brought into it .
This isn 't evident from the film .
Instead , you get the famous movement of the hand .
Also in the script , Elizabeth passes out at this point
in the excitement of it all ,
but she seems to somehow keep control of herself
[ CHUCKLES ] during the film version .
And now , " It 's alive . "
In 1823 , it was , " ' It lives , ' said Frankenstein . "
" It 's alive . " He 's supposed to say it twice in the script ,
he says it seven times in the film .
" It 's alive , it 's alive , " building up into this hysteria
that James Whale mentioned .
Partly ' cause he 's playing up to the audience ,
partly because this is the great moment of his life .
Now I know what it feels like ...
FRAYLING : " Now I know what it feels like to be God , "
very controversial line .
Cut in some places on first release
and in all places in 1937 when it was re-released .
That line was thought to be too much , and has only recently been put back .
It was covered by a peal of thunder in the version that I saw in the 1960s ,
and only recently has " Now I know what it feels like to be God " come back .
And after the intensity of that ,
another over-lit domestic scene and change of mood .
James Whale 's personal taste in interior design
with lots of silver , lots of flowers , lots of candelabra , lots of paneling .
He liked that sort of design ,
and tends to have his domestic scenes in those sort of settings ,
in this case with mullioned windows .
And the old Baron , because Frankenstein is the son of a baron ,
he 's gone up market since the novel , where he 's simply a scientist .
The Baron is played by Frederick Kerr , 73 years old ,
old-style British actor who played the father , the deaf father ,
In Whale 's previous film , Waterloo Bridge .
Cantankerous , bucolic , ruddy , portly ,
and lots of extra comedy added after the shooting script stage
in order to turn him into even more of a burlesque character .
He 's also a bully , and there 's a sub-theme running through Frankenstein
which Whale emphasized , of how the father is very tyrannical
and the young scientist is rather desperate to impress him ,
but is unable to do so .
That isn 't in the script at all ,
but it seems to have emerged at the last minute .
Frankenstein says later in the film , " My father never believes in anyone , "
whereas in the script it said ,
" My father will believe when the rest of the world does . "
Thank you , Herr Vogel .
Both in my private and official capacities as Burgomaster ...
FRAYLING : And this piece of officialdom , in the form of the Burgomaster ,
who comes in to be pushed around by the Baron ,
and you get this comedy of eccentricity , comedy of manners ,
comedy of social gradations .
James Whale was a bit of a snob .
He was himself from a working class family in Dudley , Worcestershire ,
the son of a blast-furnace man and a nurse ,
and he had many , many brothers and sisters .
And when he came to Hollywood , he remade his curriculum vitae .
Shortly after Frankenstein came out , he reduced several years off his age
so he went from his 40s into his 30s . He claimed that he had a private tutor
and he liked to look up his family tree to see if there was any nobility
hidden in the Whale family in the dim and distant past .
So social things meant a lot to James Whale ,
and this comedy of manners has a kind of edge to it .
I mean , the Baron is pushing around officialdom .
He 's only doing his job , after all , but that becomes a comedy issue .
And this is like a West End play
or a Broadway play of a certain kind in the 1920s ,
where comedy of manners was the heart of the comedy .
What do you mean , " No , no " ?
- What about his work ? - Stuff and nonsense !
What about his wedding ?
There is another woman ,
and I 'm going to find her .
FRAYLING : In the script , we then go back to the laboratory ,
where Frankenstein is pacing up and down in a nervous way ,
where you see the creature for the first time ,
the " creature " in the novel , the " monster " in the film from the word go ,
whereas in the film , it 's Waldman that 's pacing up and down .
But a nice design touch , the equipment is covered in white sheets
as if there are ghosts standing behind the two scientists ,
the ghosts of the previous scene .
That 's not mentioned at all on the shooting script .
Poor old Waldman .
FRAYLING : In a famous speech coming up which isn 't on the shooting script at all ,
which many think was added by Whale ,
the great speech about , " Don 't you ever overreach , "
" don 't you ever try to push the envelope , "
" don 't you ever try to do something dangerous ? "
" Why are you so conventional ? "
And people have reckoned that this maybe is James Whale speaking ,
it could equally be a focus on the theme of overreaching ,
the Promethean theme in the film , the Faustian theme ,
actually distilled into a serious speech .
Whale obviously thought this was the moment
to do a head-on , close-up speech about the dangers of overreaching ,
Icarus getting his wings singed , Faust blowing himself up ,
Adam eating the fruit of the tree of knowledge .
Critics of this kind of philosophy of science , if I can put it that way ,
have often complained that films like this put people off a scientific career
and create a sort of anti-science attitude in society .
But actually , there 's rather a marvelous by-product
of the laboratory scene we 've just seen .
Dr. Jean Rosenbaum of New Mexico later admitted
that he first got the idea of the cardiac pacemaker , his invention ,
it came to him in 1951 when he recalled being scared as a child
by the laboratory scene in Frankenstein .
Absurd as this drama may be to sophisticated audiences of today ,
it put in mind this idea of sparking a heart into life .
And so , one of the spin-offs of the lab scene
is the cardiac pacemaker .
Overreaching sometimes leads in interesting directions .
... and it will destroy you !
Patience , patience .
FRAYLING : And of course , this is the moment when Frankenstein discovers
that Fritz has put the wrong brain , this eugenic theme ,
into his creature .
And there 's that wonderful double-take as Colin Clive realizes
that despite his best intentions , this is likely to go seriously wrong .
And there 's an interesting ambiguity about this ,
because in the John Balderston version and the Robert Florey outline ,
the monster comes out as a ravening , grunting beast
who really doesn 't have any redeeming features .
He 's got this dysfunctio cerebri sewn into him ,
so he 's going to be a complete psychopath .
But actually , Boris Karloff played it , under Whale 's direction ,
as a sympathetic portrayal .
So although he 's got this terrible start in life , there 's also sympathy for the character ,
which , of course , made that theme much more subtle .
" In the script , " The door slowly opens , revealing The Monster in the frame .
" The Monster is a strangely hideous , grotesque , inhuman figure , "
" only the semblance of humanity . "
And here we have a series of close-ups by Whale
to introduce us to this astonishing image of Boris Karloff with his makeup .
The bolt through his neck , which is what you plug him into ,
the sawn-off cranium , flat top with the hair brushed forward over it ,
which is how they put his brain in .
The sunken cheeks , the wonderful doe-like eyes ,
and the way he walks by leaning forward .
It says in the script , " He must not walk like a robot . "
And one of the design ideas for the creature , as late as 1930 ,
by Universal artists ,
was , in fact , a robot , a mechanical monster ,
or a Neanderthal sort of figure ,
or maybe someone whose brains were on the outside ,
a sort of bug-eyed monster or an alien figure , maybe The Monster should look like that .
But no , he has this extraordinary sympathetic look ,
which enables Karloff 's facial features to be as mobile as they need to be
even though there 's makeup
that took three and a half hours to apply every morning on top of it .
Jack Pierce , the makeup man , the head of makeup at Universal ,
who was responsible for the makeup , with James Whale ,
talked about how he got a lot of his ideas
from anatomical books and medical books and scientific research .
And he actually did research on what happens to bodies after decomposition
and one of the things that happens is that a lot of liquid goes into the extremities ,
so you get big hands and big feet .
And people writing about the mummies of ancient Egypt
had said that that 's one of the by-products of being buried .
So , Karloff has these big hands and big feet with the asphalt spreader 's boots
and he almost looks like a sort of strange American working man ,
except that he 's wearing a suit that 's too small for him
that 's supposed to be a cast-off from Frankenstein .
And from the medical textbooks ,
he looks also as though he 's got an acromegalic condition .
An image of disability rather than monstrosity ,
which I suspect that Jack Pierce used when developing his makeup .
Boris Karloff had been in Hollywood for 10 years ,
had appeared in over 80 movies . His real name was William Henry Pratt .
He was born in Dulwich , England ,
and most recently was appearing in a gangster film called Graft ,
which is why he was on the Universal lot when James Whale found him .
And he 'd also appeared in The Criminal Code
as a murdering jailbird in Howard Hawks ' film .
But he really wasn 't making a success of his career ,
and this , for him , was the turning point .
A wonderful piece of pantomime with the hands
grasping towards the light of the skylight , again this theme of light and flame .
There 's good light , the light that gave him the vital spark ,
the light of the heavens , the light of the sun ,
and there 's bad light , the light of the flambeau ,
the light of the gravedigger 's pipe , the light of the flaming torch ,
the light of the mill at the end as The Monster gets destroyed .
Good fire and bad fire .
It 's a kind of visualization of the theme of the modern Prometheus .
In the shooting script , which was dated August , 1931 ,
so it was a very recent one ,
the fire , in fact , comes from matches being struck on the floor
and the lighting of cigarettes , which causes The Monster to go haywire .
And Frankenstein keeps striking matches on the floor
in order to keep him at bay .
But the flaming torch is a sort of medieval concept .
Again this timelessness , you know , " What sort of period are we in ? "
Is brought in instead .
[ CLATTERING ]
Now we 're down in the very expressionist cellar
of the watchtower .
Lots of diagonals , lots of beams , lots of slanting walls .
A world that 's about to totter over ,
and Fritz is tormenting the creature with a whip .
In the Balderston version , it was Frankenstein that tormented the creature ,
but actually , Frankenstein is holding Fritz back .
Oh , come away , Fritz .
FRAYLING : Sad moment .
" Leave it alone . Leave it alone . "
Again , a line that was added at the last minute .
Colin Clive being very touching , realizing that his life 's work
is going very seriously wrong .
The censors were worried about the close-ups
of the tormenting by Fritz of the creature
and these were trimmed when the film actually went on release
at the end of 1931 .
It was thought to be going a bit far .
In the shooting script , there 's another scene here set in the village
where you had the villagers scurrying around the main street
hearing the howls of the creature and the noises from the cellar
and looking up at the watchtower on the hill ,
and realizing that something very strange is going on .
But in the film , we cut straight to Waldman and Frankenstein
rushing down into the cellar , down those stone steps
which Fritz had had so much comedy coming down earlier ,
and trying to see what 's going on .
It 's the death of Fritz , who 's hung up .
In England , the censor was very worried about this shot
of seeing Fritz actually hanging from the cellar ,
and it was trimmed .
[ SNARLING ]
Danny Hall 's design , Herman Rosse 's design ,
are really an embodiment of what the script says about the cellar ,
" Dark , old beams , sagging a little with age , "
" support the low roof . "
" The walls are damp and covered with fungus . "
" A suitable place for the creature to live in . "
And Karloff , whose performance is so extraordinary and sympathetic
as the creature , even while he 's raving in this way ,
actually said about his performance ,
" This was a pathetic creature who , like us all , "
" had neither wish nor say in his creation , "
" and certainly did not wish upon itself the hideous image "
" which automatically terrified humans whom it tried to befriend . "
He much preferred it to be called " creature " rather than " monster . "
And in fact , in Mary Shelley 's original novel ,
the epigraph on the front page was a quote from Milton 's Paradise Lost ,
" Did I request thee , Maker , from my clay To mold me Man ? "
" Did I ask to be brought into the world ? "
As Karloff said , it was as though man , in his blundering , searching attempts
to improve himself , was to find himself deserted by his God .
Karloff didn 't ask to be created , and he 's been deserted by his creator ,
who won 't take responsibility for him .
He 's taken one look at him and he 's run for it .
And now , they 've got to do damage limitation .
And this is one of the great subtleties ,
people have , again , projected this onto James Whale ,
gay , an outsider , a very theatrical sort of character ,
rather shy inside ,
and maybe he was identifying with the creature .
Well , maybe he was , maybe he wasn 't , it 's in the original novel ,
and it 's one of the great performances ,
almost like a silent film performance or pantomime .
The death of Fritz is interesting ' cause in the novel ,
the creature is unable to have a family of his own .
He 's the product of a cybernetic birth .
He has a father , but no mother , he 's been created by the father .
And in revenge for this , he gets his own back on Frankenstein 's family .
He murders Frankenstein 's little brother , William ,
which is the novel 's version of the Little Maria sequence
that comes a little later , in a field just outside Geneva .
He murders Frankenstein 's close friend , Henry Clerval ,
and then he murders Elizabeth , his bride ,
because in the book she has just become his bride ,
and he murders her , as well .
If he can 't have a family ,
Frankenstein 's not going to be allowed one either .
" I will be with you on your wedding night . "
But in the film , it 's a more indiscriminate sort of murdering creature .
He kills Fritz , and later on , Little Maria , as we 'll see ,
and there 's no connection with the family in the way that the novel had .
So some of the themes of the novel , this idea of cybernetic birth ,
birthing , an allegory of birthing ...
Mary Shelley had recently lost her own baby .
All of that gets lost in ruthlessly paring it down
to a story about the social responsibility of science
for Depression audiences .
One might wonder whether Depression audiences
enjoyed a film like this that was so gloomy
and the Motion Picture Herald , when it came out , said ,
" People like the tragic best at those times "
" when their own spirits are depressed . "
" And the economists tell us that even more than their spirits "
" are at a low ebb . "
In other words , horror movies , this new genre ,
might actually appeal to people who in real life are rather depressed .
And maybe some of the themes of the film actually relate
to the atmosphere in America in 1931 rather than in Geneva in 1816
or in London when the play was produced in 1823 .
This movie is as much about America at the time it was released ,
the frustration of not being able to do something about it .
You know , Karloff looks like an American working man
and the sheer frustration of not being able to express himself
is an important part of this .
The experts have let us down , the people behind the stock market ,
the economists , the policy-makers , they 've let us down ,
just as Frankenstein lets down the creature .
And there is a kind of allegory of depression going on here
which would have no doubt have clicked with the audiences .
And contemporary critics picked up on this .
Of course , the articulacy of the creature is an interesting aspect of this .
In all theatrical versions from 1823 onwards ,
he 's a grunting monster .
In the book , he 's very , very articulate .
He stumbles around the woods and comes across a cottage ,
where he watches the De Lacey family educating their children ,
and he picks this up .
It 's an early version of distance learning .
And he picks up language and understanding
and philosophy and argument
and articulacy and morals
from his watching of this family .
He also finds a satchel , which has in it various books ,
including Goethe 's The Sorrows of Young Werther ,
Plutarch 's Lives ,
and Milton 's Paradise Lost , of course . The fallen angel , forbidden knowledge .
And after that , you can 't stop him talking .
And there 's a famous meeting between the scientist and his creation
on the Mer de Glace at Chamonix in the Alps in France ,
where they talk moral philosophy .
Well , in the film , all that 's cut out ,
just like the dysfunctional brain cuts out a lot of the social responsibility theme ,
ruthlessly pared down so he 's a grunting creature .
Only in the second film , The Bride of Frankenstein ,
will the Karloff character become articulate , and the De Lacey scene will be put back .
It 's all my fault .
- Get him on the sofa . - Come on .
Oh . Oh , my boy .
Thank you .
FRAYLING : In the shooting script , there 's an interesting moment here
where Waldman says to Frankenstein , " When you are well , we will write , "
his research , " in a book for the world lo read . "
" Yes , " says Frankenstein , " the world must know . "
All of this must lead somewhere ,
it must add to the sum total of human knowledge ,
it must turn into science .
All that went from the final version ,
where there 's no sense that positive results are coming from this at all .
[ PANTING ] No , I can 't . My work .
What will happen to the records of my experiment ?
We will preserve them .
- And ... - I will see that it is painlessly destroyed .
" We will preserve the records , " rather than " We 're going to write a book together . "
Waldman is not that sympathetic a character
that he 's actually going into partnership with Frankenstein .
" He 's the guy who says , " Kill , kill , kill .
" This is a nasty character , and the world isn 't ready for him . "
In the novel , Waldman is in fact the progressive scientist at the medical institute ,
the professor of chemistry , who actually encourages Frankenstein to overreach ,
as opposed to the professor of natural philosophy , who holds him back .
It 's Waldman who , in a lecture , says to the assembled students ,
" The ancient teachers promised impossibilities , "
" the modern masters promise very little . "
" Why doesn 't modern science promise more ? "
And this sows the seed in Frankenstein 's mind
of overreaching and actually creating life .
One thing in the text that isn 't clear
is why the creature should be eight-foot-tall in the novel ,
when , in fact , he 's been made out of pieces of bodies .
And a clue to this is that
Mary Shelley says that the body parts of the creature
were found from dissecting rooms and graveyards ,
and medical experiments and charnel houses ,
but also from slaughterhouses .
And it 's an interesting word
because it suggests there 's animal parts inside the creature as well as human ones ,
which might explain the strange scale .
In the film , his boots are built up
and he 's seven-foot-tall rather than eight-foot-tall ,
but he 's obviously larger than life .
Larger than life in every way ,
as Mel Brooks made into the subject of lots of comedy in Young Frankenstein .
But it 's one of the ambiguities of the novel .
Another ambiguity in the novel
is what Mary Shelley thought the creature should look like .
The first thing she wrote was the laboratory scene .
" It was in a dreary night of November that I beheld ... " Et cetera .
But then she goes on to describe what the creature looks like .
" His limbs were in proportion , and I 'd selected his features as beautiful . "
" Beautiful ! Great God ! "
" His yellow skin scarcely covered the work of muscles and arteries beneath , "
" his hair was of a lustrous black and flowing , and his teeth of a pearly whiteness . "
At one level , he 's very beautiful ,
because his body parts have been selected with such care .
But when you look at his eyes ,
you see that there 's " a horrid contrast , " as she puts it , with his body .
" His watery eyes are a mirror of his soul , " and there 's something ...
Or has he got a soul ?
And there 's something going on behind those eyes that 's not very nice .
That 's all really quite subtle , and people notice there 's something wrong with him .
And later on he 's described as getting increasingly ugly ,
as an outward sign of how people treat him .
In the film , again , a huge shortcut .
He 's a bug-eyed monster from the word go .
Not really bug-eyed , doe-eyed monster in Karloff 's performance .
But that again is a kind of shortcut .
And it turns the novel into something else ,
from a piece of literature into a piece of mythology .
I suppose Karloff 's makeup is up there
with Charlie Chaplin 's bowler hat and Mickey Mouse 's ears
as one of the great icons of Hollywood cinema ,
recognizable anywhere in the world .
- Let 's make it soon . - As soon as you like .
FRAYLING : And now , after that darkness to light , to the villa , to the lake ,
we could even be in Switzerland , like in the original story .
And it 's all jollity for the wedding ,
where these artificial orange blossoms
are part of the Frankenstein family tradition on wedding days .
And the little miniature ,
which shows Baron and Baroness Frankenstein ,
is the only reference to Frankenstein 's mother
in the entire film .
It 's a film about a motherless child , a cybernetic birth ,
and the female is missing at all sorts of different levels .
This little miniature is actually quite important .
A lot of comedy with the Baron
turned into even more of a cantankerous , sort of comedic character by James Whale .
" And the whole gag about " My grandmother wouldn 't let him drink the wine
" and therefore the wine has been saved in the cellar "
was added by James Whale at the last minute .
As was the maids all having a glass of champagne ,
because the Baron doesn 't want to waste his best wine on them .
The maids will appear at the very end
in the happy epilogue that was added at the last minute .
All of that came from James Whale .
All full ? Yes ? Come along .
Here 's a health to a son of the house of Frankenstein .
FRAYLING : Son to the house of Frankenstein .
The irony , as Frankenstein 's created this artificial son
who is rampaging around the countryside while they speak .
So the toast is , " A son to the house of Frankenstein . "
And this irony is underlined several times from now on .
And here we have a brightly lit set with paneling and flowers ,
and champagne and champagne glasses .
The other side of the design of the film Frankenstein .
Darkness , expressionism , angularity , shadows .
And then brightness , social comedy , eccentricity , snobbery ,
and the staginess , theatricality .
Whale absolutely loved that .
Isn 't it wonderful ?
And with the garlands of flowers and the baronial coats of arms up by the ceiling ,
and a very , very cluttered set .
Danny Hall was capable of doing these as well as the more expressionist ones .
And now we 're out in the village for the first time in the film ,
although not in the shooting script .
And the village was designed by Danny Hall for All Quiet on the Western Front
the year before Frankenstein .
It was a standing set , a very large set , on the back lot at Universal ,
a German village .
And it was recycled for Frankenstein .
And indeed used for all the subsequent Universal Frankenstein films as well .
- Well , I suppose I 'd better show myself . - Make a little talk .
[ CHURCH BELLS TOLLING ]
[ ALL CHEERING ]
FRAYLING : The bells peal out the joy of wedding time .
We 've had the funeral bells at the beginning , this is the wedding bells ,
and we 'll have a tolling bell of doom in the last sequence as well .
In the absence of music , the use of sound ,
whether it 's crackling electrics or bells or the sounds of the laboratory ,
the sounds of merrymaking is a very ...
You know , this is only a couple of years after sound properly came in ,
and James Whale is often accused of being a very theatrical , static kind of director ,
and I think these sequences give the lie to that .
A long , long tracking shot down the village to show off the great set that Universal had ,
with all the merrymaking villagers .
Are we in the Tirol ? Are we in Switzerland ?
Are we in Bavaria ,
which is where Carl Laemmle , the head of the studio , came from ?
I don 't know . It 's Ruritania . It 's never-never land .
And now we 're by the side of the lake . It was filmed at Malibou Lake ,
a rare location moment in this film ,
where Little Maria is playing .
She 's played by the seven-year-old Marilyn Harris .
And this sequence was shot on September 28 , 29 , 1931 .
The film was shot largely in sequence ,
so we 'd been shooting since the end of August .
They had been filming for a month .
And this is the famous scene by the lake .
In the film , the father , Ludwig , goes off and leaves the little girl to play by herself .
In the shooting script , interestingly , it 's her mother who leaves her to play ,
a buxom peasant woman in her early 30s ,
who goes into the kitchen of the cottage and leaves her child playing by the lakeside .
So she could conceivably have seen what happens now ,
which is how everyone knows that it 's a murder later on .
In the absence of anyone actually seeing what happened ,
we don 't quite know why they immediately jump to the conclusion
that it 's a murder .
This very , very touching scene
that stimulated , for example ,
inspired a Spanish film of 1973 , The Spirit of the Beehive ,
Víctor Erice ,
which is all about a little girl who grows up in Franco 's Spain ,
and for whom this sequence means so much .
It helps her understand adult life ,
it helps her to navigate the difficulties of grown-up life .
So it had a really touching afterlife .
And this was a slightly controversial scene
in that Karloff wasn 't sure that James Whale was playing it the right way .
In the shooting script , he places the little girl on the surface of the water ,
an expectant smile on his face .
" The flowers float , they 're little boats , so maybe the little girl will float as well . "
So he places heron the surface of the water ,
a reference to the scene where little William Frankenstein is killed in the novel ,
Frankenstein 's younger brother ,
and where his disabled sister is thrown in the lake
in Peggy Webling 's version , off-stage .
Here , it 's a little girl who has no connection with the family ,
but who doesn 't have any problem playing games with the creature .
See how mine floats ?
FRAYLING : Very , very touching moment by Karloff .
This is the first person who 's been nice to him in his life ,
and he just doesn 't know how to behave .
But sheer excitement , like a child , as he throws the flowers in .
But then he picks up the child and chucks her into the lake .
And Karloff thought that the original version ,
which is placing her gently on the surface of the lake ,
would 've been slightly less gruesome .
He actually hurls her into the lake .
And there was originally a shot , a close-up , of her struggling in the water and drowning .
So with the best intentions in the world , he 's destroyed the thing he loves .
And off he goes into the woods ,
completely confused by the one character who 's been nice to him ,
and he 's destroyed it , unwittingly .
" But Whale said , " We must have him actually throwing the child in the lake .
" You see , it 's all part of the ritual . "
That you have to have a moment like this
for the final sequences actually to make sense .
[ CHEERFUL MUSIC PLAYING ]
And then we cut back to the All Quiet on the Western Front village ,
where the lederhosen and the merry-go-rounds
and the excitement of the wedding are in full swing .
Some people reckon these sequences go on a bit long ,
they 're showing off about the production values
of having a few extras all dressed up in Tyrolean costumes .
And maybe James Whale overdoes it , but the reason for this is ...
It 's like in a Western , where you have the merrymaking or the saloon scene ,
and someone walks in and spoils the party .
" The Indians are coming ! "
Well , in this case , it 's Little Maria .
And in the shooting script , it 's the mother who carried the child up the street .
In the film , it 's the father , Ludwig .
When the Little Maria sequence was pruned ,
in some places , on first release , in many places , in 1937 ,
it finished with the Karloff character leaning forward in this expectant way ,
and cut to the next time we see her , being carried up the street by her father .
It actually created the impression that the child had been molested ,
the child had been raped in some way ,
and had been murdered .
It 's an extraordinary example of how censorship can actually make things worse .
Because when the sequence is put back together again ,
it 's actually rather touching .
Well , what is it ?
FRAYLING : And then , after that darkness , into the light .
The day of the wedding ,
with this astonishing bridal train and bridal gown for Mae Clarke .
In the shooting script , this takes place in the bedroom .
It isn 't clear whether this is an adjunct to the living room or the bedroom .
It 's a strange place to be
on wedding morning in a traditional baronial household .
But she has a feeling that something is wrong .
Where 's Dr. Waldman ? Why is he late for the wedding ?
Oh , he 's always late .
FRAYLING : Victor comes in , in the shooting script , and says ,
" Waldman has been murdered . They found him in the watchtower . "
" It 's loose now . People have seen him in the hills . "
" Shepherds are found dead next to their flocks . "
Lots of explanation of the creature having got away from the watchtower
and rampaging around the countryside .
It 's very , very cryptic in the film version .
I think Whale felt that it slowed things down , so he cuts Victor 's dialogue ,
and as a result , we don 't actually quite know what goes on .
Also in the shooting script ,
Frankenstein puts on her head the orange blossom wreath ,
which he 's been given by the Baron , still in his hand
because , actually , this scene was continuous from the wedding scene ,
and the Little Maria scene came later in the shooting script .
It 's still in his hand ,
and he places the orange blossom wreath on her head to reassure her ,
so that when she 's attacked by the creature , she has the orange blossom on her head .
Which is rather a nice touch .
How beautiful you look .
- VICTOR : Henry ! Henry ! - [ KNOCKING ON DOOR ]
What 's that ?
FRAYLING : Here 's Victor , coming in with his news .
- Dr . Waldman ! - What about Dr. Waldman ?
- Henry , don 't leave me . Don 't leave me . - No , darling , you stay here .
Henry . Henry !
FRAYLING : Why does he lock the door ?
He locked the door of the laboratory
to make sure he wasn 't interrupted during the operation scene ,
and he 's heard about Dr. Waldman , and he locks the door .
It 's a sort of paranoid reflex that he should be secret .
Of course , it actually causes all sorts of problems later on .
And here we have a rather farfetched set of moments ,
where the creature appears to be something of a ventriloquist .
" It 's upstairs ! " So they look upstairs .
" It 's in the cellar ! " So they look in the cellar .
" It 's Elizabeth ! " So they go back to the living room / bedroom .
Either the creature is very good at throwing his voice
or they can 't quite tell where the sound is coming from .
But it 's an excuse for James Whale 's camera
to wander round the Frankenstein household
and go through walls in a way that he rather enjoyed doing .
Now , this sequence is taken directly from The Cabinet of Dr. Caligari
by Robert Wiene , 1919 ,
where the somnambulist , Cesare , is standing at the window ,
comes in , and the girl , played by Lil Dagover , is asleep .
And it became a classic of expressionist cinema ,
the woman under threat , the woman in the bridal gown ,
the woman in her chemise , the woman in her nightclothes ,
and the threat , coming in through the window .
And it 's a silent film moment , this ,
because in his huge asphalt spreader 's boots ,
she 'd have heard the creature behind her .
But she doesn 't , and so the scream is a kind of delayed drop .
When they were filming this sequence ,
which is only cryptically mentioned in the shooting script ,
James Whale said to Mae Clarke ,
" Now you 've all read the script . Let 's do the mechanics . "
And he made the scene much more elaborate in the actual acting of it .
The slow burn of the creature stepping forward ,
and then a shot taken directly from a famous painting
by Johann Heinrich Füssli , John Henry Fuseli ,
called The Nightmare , of the girl draped over the bed ,
in the case of the painting , with the nightmare perched upon her chest .
And it 's taken directly from it ,
and it was used in the advertising for the film ,
in the posters , the tie-in book , this image from The Nightmare .
In the shooting script , you see that moment from the door frame .
You get a completely different angle on it .
And also in the shooting script , Elizabeth is lying across the bed ,
apparently dead , her wedding gown is in tatters , and there 's a sense ,
she doesn 't say anything , she just falls back ,
that she has been killed , as in the novel .
The creature has actually killed Elizabeth , Frankenstein 's fiancée .
But it 's left ambiguous , and of course we 'll learn later that she survived .
But it 's an interesting use of a northern European painting
to sort out a visual problem
and create this image of the woman draped over the bed .
A lot of northern European émigrés
came to Hollywood as production designers and art directors
and brought that aesthetic with them .
German expressionism , German symbolism ,
19th-century German painting , Romantic painting .
And you see lots and lots of references , particularly in horror movies ,
to that whole European tradition of art ,
and Whale was consciously using it .
[ CHURCH BELLS TOLLING ]
[ PEOPLE SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY ]
[ ALL CLAMORING ]
And now we have the merrymaking
interrupted by Little Maria and her father going to see the Burgomaster .
Not little William , the brother ,
not little Katrina , the sister from the Peggy Webling play ,
but Little Maria and the father .
And they 're going to the Burgomaster because they are convinced that it 's murder .
It 's a public issue . It 's not just an accident .
Again , in the shooting script ,
the mother could have seen that it wasn 't an accident ,
but this is now an assumption on the part of the mob ,
and the mob begins to become , more and more ,
a character in the play now .
A drunken , raging mob . They 've had too much to drink .
The Baron predicted
that when they started having a hangover , they 'd start fighting each other .
And instead , they turn into this rather ugly , raging mob
that acts like a single unit for the rest of the film ,
which was much parodied later on in Young Frankenstein by Mel Brooks .
It 's no longer flaming torches and stones ,
it 's rotten tomatoes [ CHUCKLES ] that get thrown at the creature .
But this idea of the mob as a character in the film
really dominates the last part .
And here 's Frankenstein in his jodhpurs and sports jacket ,
no longer in his wedding outfit ,
suggesting that Victor , if all goes wrong , Victor should take over ,
and , indeed , he might marry Elizabeth .
So Elizabeth survived .
Maybe this is a hangover from the John Balderston version ,
where Victor was the ex-fiancé of Elizabeth .
In fact , there are various hangovers from earlier scripts
that don 't quite work in the film .
Earlier on , the Baron has referred
to Frankenstein 's experiments " in the old mill . "
To Frankenstein 's experiments " in the old mill . "
And they were , indeed , taking place in the old mill in the Robert Florey version ,
but in this version , they 're taking place in the watchtower
and somehow , no one noticed that continuity error .
So , in some senses , the final version bears the stamp
of the myriad of interpretations of Frankenstein
which had happened in order to turn it into a movie .
As late as early 1931 , in the studio , someone wrote a memo
saying they didn 't think that this was an adaptable property .
It was too complicated .
The novel consisted of memoirs and letters
and the autobiography of the creature ,
and it was three volumes , and lots and lots of disquisitions
on all the social , political , economic , scientific , psychological theories
that Mary Shelley was interested in .
How could you adapt that into a crisp , short horror movie ?
Well , we 've seen various ways in which shortcuts were taken .
The brain , the laboratory sequence , the creature and its makeup .
And in that process , some loose trails were left .
[ DOGS BARKING ]
[ PEOPLE CLAMORING ]
Here , a very gendered approach to the village .
The women are at the windows ,
the women are standing at the edge of the main street , crossing themselves ,
while the men go out hunting in the woods , in the mountains , in the lake ,
in the various sectors that they 've been apportioned by the Burgomaster .
Frankenstein has said ,
" I made him with these hands , and with these hands , I will destroy him . "
And there 's much emphasis in the novel , as well ,
of how Frankenstein created the creature with his hands .
And recent criticism has suggested this isn 't just a reference to craftsmanship ,
a handmade creature ,
but also , it might be a reference to masturbation .
That , actually , with these hands , Frankenstein has been a semen donor
in order to create this new life on the slab .
If so , I 'm not sure that the Production Code
would later have allowed the line " I made him with these hands "
to get through .
But maybe that 's reading into it .
This way !
Come on , men !
[ ALL CLAMORING ]
FRAYLING : So now we 're actually building up to the climax
with the flaming torches and the villagers looking for the creature .
In the shooting script , there 's much more emphasis on the Baron at this point .
The Baron , who gets lost in the crowd and keeps saying ,
" is my son among you ? Where 's my son ? Have you seen my son ? "
And towards the end , when they want to burn the mill ,
he says , " No , you mustn 't do that . You must save my son . "
And there 's a touching feeling that the relationship between them ,
which started off so negatively ,
" My father never believed anything about me , "
actually is beginning to get closer as a result of this crisis .
But that 's all gone in the James Whale version .
We just have Frankenstein saying , " My father never understands me . "
And really , he disappears from the plot at this point .
The rest , come with me .
[ DOGS BARKING ]
So here we are amongst the studio rocks , rather like the ones we began with ,
with the gibbet and the discovery of the corpse
against an angry sky , a lowering sky ,
rather a crinkled backdrop , actually , if you look closely ,
And this is the equivalent of the Chamonix scene in the novel ,
where the creature finally meets his maker .
And instead of a long discussion about ethics and the meaning of life ,
and will Frankenstein create a mate for him ,
we have the creature getting his revenge at last .
This injured villager lying in the hills
was added after the shooting script stage ,
and is probably a visualization of the line from Victor earlier ,
about shepherds being hurt and killed out in the fields ,
only they leave it till now .
And also that it can direct people in two directions ,
so that Frankenstein can be isolated when he meets the creature .
In the script , there 's lots of reference to how ugly the mob has become at this stage .
Their angry , sweating faces , the baying of the hounds .
What scent are the hounds after ?
In the script , a piece of the creature 's jacket is found ,
and it 's shown to the hounds , and that explains why they 're on the scent .
We don 't quite know why they 're on the scent in this version .
But you 've got the baying of the hounds , the angry mob , the flaming torches ,
and there 's a sense of , you know ...
Another aspect of the sympathy we feel for the creature
is that this is kind of mass behavior of a fairly mindless kind .
They 're just out to kill the bogeyman .
Herr Frankenstein ! Where are you ?
[ DOGS HOWLING ]
- I think he 's up there . Come on , follow him . - Follow him .
FRAYLING : By now , the filming was at the very end of September ,
beginning of October , 1931 .
They 'd started on August the 24th .
They were a couple of days over schedule and a little bit over budget , but not much .
And having shot in sequence , they were building up to the final sequences
set in the mill .
The reason they were set in a mill was from Robert Florey 's outline .
He reckoned that the operation should take place in an old mill ,
but so should the climax .
And the creature would make his way back to the old mill ,
because that 's where his origins came from .
It was finding his way home , finding his way back into the womb ,
and this rickety old mill was the womb .
The reason he chose a mill , Florey said , was that he had an apartment in Los Angeles
which overlooked a branch of Van de Kamp Bakery ,
which had a mill as its corporate image .
And while he was doing the outline , it gave him the idea .
That may or may not be so .
Actually , there 's some early versions of the Frankenstein play in the 1820s and ' 30s
where the creature is killed in all sorts of outlandish ways .
In an avalanche , falling over a cliff ,
and in one of them , he dies in an old , burning mill .
So it 's not quite clear where that came from .
This way . Come on . Hurry . Hurry !
[ ALL SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
[ DOGS BARKING ]
There ! Turn the hounds loose !
FRAYLING : The famous moment where the creature
carries his creator away over his shoulder
and Karloff complained that Colin Clive was actually pretty heavy ,
and it caused all sorts of back problems for him later in life .
The mill is exactly like the production drawing
by Herman Rosse under the guidance of Danny Hall .
A great expressionist mill , with tattered sails hanging in shreds ,
and the wood 's falling off it . It 's a decaying flour mill .
And a confined space forgoing up , up , up .
The creature is going up to the light , to the sky , where he came from .
I mean , why is he taking Frankenstein out to the mill ?
Does he simply want to murder him in front of the peasants ,
or is he making for the heavens ?
MAN : Once more .
[ GRUNTING ]
FRAYLING : The scene of the gear going round ,
and seeing the faces of the two protagonists
actually framed by the wooden gearing mechanism
was added by James Whale on the set .
So like a lot of the more visual moments in the film ,
it was actually quite a last-minute decision ,
in order to make the film more exciting visually ,
and give it a bit of style .
It 's a particularly expressionist moment ,
where expressionist films often framed the image through arches , through windows ,
in order to create unusual shapes to the screen for the viewer to watch them .
Well , this was framed through the gearing mechanism .
And it creates an unusual shape to frame the two protagonists
for this climactic confrontation .
Now , what happens now was very muddled in the film ,
and no one was quite sure what to do .
Frankenstein , in ...
It 's clear from the shooting script that Frankenstein gets killed .
" His lifeless body . "
The same phrase that 's applied to Elizabeth , " Her lifeless body . "
So , as in the novel , they both die .
In the case of the novel , it 's at the North Pole ,
and then the creature goes off on an ice floe into the distance .
But clearly , either they wanted a sequel
or they thought it was too unhappy an ending ,
although Colin Clive thought it was one of the strengths , actually , of the film ,
that it dared to have an unhappy ending .
They decided to make Frankenstein survive , and added the moment
where he 's thrown over the parapet and lands on the sails of the windmill ,
which isn 't mentioned in the shooting script , which breaks his fall .
And then he lands on the ground and he 's okay .
And an epilogue is added
where the Baron back-announces the joke
about the grandmother not letting the wine be drunk
and the maids reappear , the ones who drank the champagne earlier ,
and it 's all light , and all is sweetness and light
after the darkness of the holocaust of the mill .
In fact , it 's called a " holocaust " in the script .
As the fire consumes the mill , the mill is a solid sheet of flame .
And in the shooting script , the film ends with a long shot of the mill burning .
But then you have this cut to this epilogue that was added subsequently .
Colin Clive was no longer around , so there 's a stand-in in the epilogue ,
just glimpsed through the open door , but it 's mainly the Baron .
And by that stage , they must have realized
that they had a great piece of myth-making in this film .
But what they couldn 't have known is that it would take over from the novel .
Everyone knows what the creature looks like . They call him " The Monster . "
Everyone knows the story of Frankenstein . Very , very few people have read the novel .
It actually took over from the literary experience
and became a piece of myth .
You could say that there 's lots of debates about intelligent design ,
and the creation myth versus the big bang ,
and other scientific explanations of the origin of the universe .
Well , I would argue that in the early 21st century ,
others have said , as well , that the real creation myth is Frankenstein .
In the age of bioengineering and tampering with biology
and genetic modification , the real creation myth is Frankenstein .
It 's the myth of a man-made universe rather than a God-made universe .
And one of the reasons why it is such a universal myth
is that this film carried it into all parts of the world .
It also Americanized it .
A British novel , turned into a British play in the 1820s ,
refracted through German expressionism in the 1920s ,
and turned into a piece of Americana in 1931 for Depression audiences .
[ CROWD CONTINUES SHOUTING ]
[ DOGS BARKING ]
- WOMAN : Have you got it ? - Yeah . Come on . Hurry .
Hurry up .
[ WHISPERING INDISTINCTLY ]
[ GIGGLING ]
FRAYLING : Here are the maids , giggling in the way that they were before .
An invention of James Whale for the fade-out ,
which is another reference to a son to the house of Frankenstein .
The great irony of the whole story of a motherless child ,
a piece of tampering with nature , versus a biological child .
You could just see that it isn 't Colin Clive lying on the bed .
He 'd gone home to London .
But this was such a relatively low-budget production
they couldn 't even get any end music specially written .
The music was written by Giuseppe Becce for silent films on the shelf ,
Grand Appassionato .
And that 's what they used behind the end credits .
Just as they used at the opening titles , Misterioso by Bernhard Kaun .
Later horror films would have special scores written for them .
This one really doesn 't .
And so ends a low-budget film that founded a genre ,
that created a corporate image for a studio
and that was imitated thousands of times , in all sorts of ways ,
for the balance of the 1930s .
Frankenstein had become a movie rather than a novel .
And on the end credits , Karloff is actually mentioned by name for the first time .
He 's a question mark on the opening credits
in a long tradition of not naming the monster .
But here he is , " The Monster , Boris Karloff . "
One , two , three ... Fourth down the cast list , and not even invited to the previews .
But it was the making of his career , and he was very grateful for it .
There were countless other Frankenstein monsters ,
but it was never to be so touching , so pathetic , again .
James Whale said the thing was to make it believable .
And he 'd certainly succeeded in that .
As Karloff wrote ,
" The most heartrending aspect of the creature 's life , "
" for us , was his ultimate desertion by his creator . "
And that had become the heart of the story .
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC PLAYING ]